Back in 2003,
بالعودة الي عام 2003،
the UK government carried out a survey.
قامت الحكومة البريطانية بعمل استطلاع رأي.
And it was a survey that measured levels of numeracy
كان الاستطلاع يقيس مستوى الإلمام بعلم الحساب
in the population.
بين السكان.
And they were shocked to find out
وكانت صدمة بالنسبة لهم عند معرفة
that for every 100 working age adults in the country,
أن بين كل 100 شخص في سن العمل في البلاد،
47 of them lacked Level 1 numeracy skills.
47 منهم يفتقرون إلى المستوى 1 للمهارات الحسابية.
Now, Level 1 numeracy skills -- that's low-end GCSE score.
المستوى 1 للمهارات الحسابية -- درجة أدنى من شهادة إتمام الثانوية العامة.
It's the ability to deal with fractions, percentages and decimals.
إنها القدرة على التعامل مع الكسور والنسب والكسور العشرية.
So this figure prompted a lot of hand-wringing in Whitehall.
فأثارت هذه الأرقام القلق في وايت هول.
Policies were changed,
تغييرت السياسات،
investments were made,
وقدمت الاستثمارات،
and then they ran the survey again in 2011.
ثم قاموا بإجراء دراسة أخرى في عام 2011.
So can you guess what happened to this number?
يمكنكم تخمين ما حدث لهذا العدد؟
It went up to 49.
ارتفع إلى 49.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And in fact, when I reported this figure in the FT,
وفي الواقع، عندما ذكرت هذا الرقم في فاينانشال تايمز،
one of our readers joked and said,
مزح أحد القراء وقال:
"This figure is only shocking to 51 percent of the population."
"يُعد هذا الرقم صدمة بالنسبة إلى 51 بالمئة فقط من السكان."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I preferred, actually, the reaction of a schoolchild
ولكن أفضل، في الواقع، رد فعل تلميذ
when I presented at a school this information,
عندما قمت بتقديم هذه المعلومات في مدرسة،
who raised their hand and said,
قام برفع يده، وقال:
"How do we know that the person who made that number
"كيف يمكن أن نتأكد أن الشخص الذي وضع هذا العدد
isn't one of the 49 percent either?"
ليس واحدا من 49 بالمئة؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So clearly, there's a numeracy issue,
بشكل واضح، يوجد مشكلة مرتبطة بالحساب،
because these are important skills for life,
لأنها تعد من المهارات المهمة للحياة،
and a lot of the changes that we want to introduce in this century
وتشمل الكثير من التغييرات التي نريد تقديمها في هذا القرن
involve us becoming more comfortable with numbers.
لجعلنا أكثر راحة مع الأرقام.
Now, it's not just an English problem.
الآن، هذه ليست مجرد مشكلة إنجليزية.
OECD this year released some figures looking at numeracy in young people,
أصدرت منظمة التعاون والتنمية هذا العام بعض الأرقام حول أساسيات الحساب لدى الشباب،
and leading the way, the USA --
تتصدر القائمة، الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية --
nearly 40 percent of young people in the US have low numeracy.
ما يقرب 40 بالمئة من الشباب في الولايات المتحدة ذوي معرفة حسابية منخفضة.
Now, England is there too,
كما انضمت انجلترا،
but there are seven OECD countries with figures above 20 percent.
ولكن هناك سبع دول من منظمة التعاون والتنمية بنسبة تفوت 20 بالمئة.
That is a problem, because it doesn't have to be that way.
هذه مشكلة، لأنه لا يجب أن يكون الأمر بهذه الطريقة.
If you look at the far end of this graph,
إذا ما نظرتم إلى آخر هذا الرسم البياني،
you can see the Netherlands and Korea are in single figures.
تستطيع أن ترى أن هولندا وكوريا تتكون من رقم واحد.
So there's definitely a numeracy problem that we want to address.
ولذلك يوجد بالتأكيد مشكلة بشأن علوم الحساب نريد حلّها.
Now, as useful as studies like these are,
بمثل إفادة دراسات كهذه،
I think we risk herding people inadvertently into one of two categories;
أعتقد أننا نخاطر عن غير قصد بتصنيف الناس في واحدة من مجموعتين،
that there are two kinds of people:
يوجد نوعان من الناس:
those people that are comfortable with numbers, that can do numbers,
أولئك الذين يشعرون بالراحة مع الأرقام، ويمكنهم التعامل معها،
and the people who can't.
وأولئك الذين لا يمكنهم التعامل معها.
And what I'm trying to talk about here today
وما أحاول التحدث عنه هنا اليوم
is to say that I believe that is a false dichotomy.
هو القول إنني أؤمن بأن هذا تصنيف زائف.
It's not an immutable pairing.
ليس اقتراناً ثابتاً.
I think you don't have to have tremendously high levels of numeracy
أعتقد أنه لا ينبغي عليك أن تتمتع بمستويات عالية جدا من المهارات الحسابية
to be inspired by numbers,
لتلهمك الأرقام،
and that should be the starting point to the journey ahead.
وينبغي أن يكون ذلك نقطة الانطلاق إلى الرحلة القادمة.
And one of the ways in which we can begin that journey, for me,
توجد طريقة واحدة يمكننا من خلالها بدء هذه الرحلة، بالنسبة لي،
is looking at statistics.
هي الاطلاع على الإحصائيات.
Now, I am the first to acknowledge that statistics has got somewhat
الآن، أنا أول من يعترف أن الإحصاءات قد حصلت إلى حد ما
of an image problem.
على صورة نمطية سيئة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's the part of mathematics
إنها جزء من الرياضيات
that even mathematicians don't particularly like,
حتى أنّ علماء الرياضيات لا يحبونها بشكل خاص،
because whereas the rest of maths is all about precision and certainty,
لأنه بينما تتمحور بقية الرياضيات حول الدقة واليقين،
statistics is almost the reverse of that.
الإحصائيات عكس ذلك تمامًا.
But actually, I was a late convert to the world of statistics myself.
ولكن في الحقيقة، تحولت إلى عالم إحصاء في وقت متأخر.
If you'd asked my undergraduate professors
إذا سألت أساتذتي قبل تخرجي
what two subjects would I be least likely to excel in after university,
عن أكثر مجالين على الأرجح قد أفشل فيهما بعد الجامعة
they'd have told you statistics and computer programming,
لكانوا سيخبرونك الإحصاءات وبرمجة الكمبيوتر،
and yet here I am, about to show you some statistical graphics
ها أنا هنا، على وشك تقديم بعض الرسومات الإحصائية
that I programmed.
التي قمت ببرمجتها.
So what inspired that change in me?
ما الذي كان مصدر إلهاما لتغيير نفسي؟
What made me think that statistics was actually an interesting thing?
ما الذي جعلني أعتقد أن الإحصاء في الواقع أمر مثيرٌ للاهتمام؟
It's really because statistics are about us.
لأن الإحصاء يتمحور حولنا.
If you look at the etymology of the word statistics,
إذا نظرتم إلى أصل كلمة علم الإحصاء أو الإحصائيات،
it's the science of dealing with data
تعني علم التعامل مع البيانات
about the state or the community that we live in.
عن الدولة أو المجتمع الذي نعيش فيه.
So statistics are about us as a group,
تتمحور الإحصائيات حولنا كمجموعة
not us as individuals.
وليس كأفراد.
And I think as social animals,
أعتقد كأشخاص اجتماعيين
we share this fascination about how we as individuals relate to our groups,
أننا نشاطر هذا الولع حول كيفية اتصالنا كأفراد مع مجموعاتنا
to our peers.
إلى أقراننا.
And statistics in this way are at their most powerful
وتعد الإحصاءات بهذه الطريقة في أشد قوتها
when they surprise us.
عندما تفاجئنا.
And there's been some really wonderful surveys carried out recently
كان هناك عدد من الاستبيانات الرائعة حقا تم إجراءها في الآونة الأخيرة
by Ipsos MORI in the last few years.
من قبل ايبسوس موري في السنوات الأخيرة
They did a survey of over 1,000 adults in the UK,
قاموا بإستبيان مع أكثر من 1000 بالغ في المملكة المتحدة،
and said, for every 100 people in England and Wales,
وسألوا، لكل 100 شخص في انكلترا وويلز،
how many of them are Muslim?
كم منهم مسلم؟
Now the average answer from this survey,
متوسط الإجابة من هذا الاستبيان،
which was supposed to be representative of the total population, was 24.
كان من المفترض أن يكون ممثلاً من مجموع عدد السكان،
That's what people thought.
كان 24
British people think 24 out of every 100 people in the country are Muslim.
الشعب البريطاني يعتقد ان 24 من كل 100 شخص في البلاد مسلمون.
Now, official figures reveal that figure to be about five.
الآن، الأرقام الرسمية تكشف أن هذا الرقم هو حوالي خمسة.
So there's this big variation between what we think, our perception,
هذا الفارق الكبير بين ما نعتقده، تصورنا
and the reality as given by statistics.
والواقع اللذي تخبرنا به الاحصاءات.
And I think that's interesting.
وأعتقد أن هذا مثير للاهتمام،
What could possibly be causing that misperception?
ما الذي قد يكون سبب سوء الفهم هذا؟
And I was so thrilled with this study,
كنت سعيدًا جدًا بهذه الدراسة
I started to take questions out in presentations. I was referring to it.
بدأت في طرح الأسئلة في العروض التقديمية. التي اشرت اليها
Now, I did a presentation
الآن، لقد قدمت عرضًا
at St. Paul's School for Girls in Hammersmith,
في مدرسة سانت بول للبنات في هامرسميث،
and I had an audience rather like this,
وكان لي جمهور مثل هذا
except it was comprised entirely of sixth-form girls.
إلا أنها كانت تتألف بالكامل من الفتيات في المرحلة الثانوية.
And I said, "Girls,
وقلت "فتيات،
how many teenage girls do you think the British public think
كم عدد الفتيات المراهقات في رأيكن
And the girls were apoplectic when I said
وكانت الفتيات مصدومات عندما قلت
the British public think that 15 out of every 100 teenage girls
بأن البريطانين يعتقدون ان 15 من كل 100 فتاة مراهقة
get pregnant in the year.
تصبح حاملًا في السنة
And they had every right to be angry,
ولهم كل الحق في الغضب،
because in fact, I'd have to have closer to 200 dots
لأنه في الواقع، يجب أن يكون أقرب إلى 200 نقطة
before I could color one in,
قبل أن أتمكن من تلوين واحد فقط
in terms of what the official figures tell us.
وفقا لما تخبرنا به الأرقام الرسمية.
And rather like numeracy, this is not just an English problem.
علي غرار الحساب، هذه ليست مجرد مشكلة إنجليزية.
Ipsos MORI expanded the survey in recent years to go across the world.
وسعت إيبسوس موري المسح في السنوات الأخيرة ليكون حول العالم.
And so, they asked Saudi Arabians,
ولذلك سألوا السعوديين لكل 100 شخص بالغ في بلدك،
how many of them are overweight or obese?
كم منهم يعاني من زيادة الوزن أو السمنة؟
And the average answer from the Saudis was just over a quarter.
ومتوسط ​​إجابات السعوديين كان أكثر بقليل من الربع.
That's what they thought.
هذا ما كانوا يعتقدونه
Just over a quarter of adults are overweight or obese.
أكثر بقليل من ربع البالغين يعاني زيادة الوزن أو السمنة.
The official figures show, actually, it's nearer to three-quarters.
وتظهر الأرقام الرسمية، أنها في الواقع أقرب إلى ثلاثة أرباع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So again, a big variation.
مرة أخرى، تباين كبير.
And I love this one: they asked in Japan, they asked the Japanese,
وأنا أحب هذا المثال: في اليابان سألوا اليابانيين
for every 100 Japanese people,
لكل 100 شخص ياباني
how many of them live in rural areas?
كم شخصًا منهم يعيش في المناطق الريفية؟
The average was about a 50-50 split, just over halfway.
وكان المتوسط ​​حوالي اكثرمن 50 بالمئة بقليل.
They thought 56 out of every 100 Japanese people lived in rural areas.
اعتقدوا أن 56 من كل 100 شخص يعيش في المناطق الريفية.
The official figure is seven.
الرقم الرسمي هو سبعة.
So extraordinary variations, and surprising to some,
تباين كبير للغاية، مثير للدهشة للبعض
but not surprising to people who have read the work
ولكن ليس مستغربًا للذين قرأوا أعمال
of Daniel Kahneman, for example, the Nobel-winning economist.
دانيال كانيمان على سبيل المثال، الإقتصادي الحائز على جائزة نوبل.
He and his colleague, Amos Tversky, spent years researching this disjoint
هو وزميله أموس تفرسكي، أمضوا سنوات من البحث في هذا الاختلاف
between what people perceive and the reality,
بين ما يظنه الناس والواقع،
the fact that people are actually pretty poor intuitive statisticians.
حقيقة أن الناس في الواقع سيئين جدًا في الإحصاءات الحدسية.
And there are many reasons for this.
وهناك أسباب كثيرة لذلك.
Individual experiences, certainly, can influence our perceptions,
التجارب الفردية، بالتأكيد يمكن أن تؤثر على تصوراتنا
but so, too, can things like the media reporting things by exception,
ولكن يمكن لأمور مثل إعلان وسائل الإعلام عن الأشياء الاستثنائية،
rather than what's normal.
بدلًا من ما هو طبيعي.
Kahneman had a nice way of referring to that.
كانيمان له طريقة لطيفة في الإشارة إلى ذلك
He said, "We can be blind to the obvious" --
قال: "يمكن أن نكون عميانًا إلى ما هو واضح"
so we've got the numbers wrong --
لذلك لدينا أرقام خاطئة
"but we can be blind to our blindness about it."
"ولكن يمكن أن نكون عميان لعمينا حيال ذلك "
And that has enormous repercussions for decision making.
وهذا له تداعيات هائلة في اتخاذ القرار.
So at the statistics office while this was all going on,
حتى في مكتب الإحصاءات بينما كان هذا كله يحدث،
I thought this was really interesting.
اعتقدت أن هذا مثير للاهتمام حقًا.
I said, this is clearly a global problem,
قلت من الواضح أنها مشكلة عالمية،
but maybe geography is the issue here.
ولكن ربما الجغرافيا هي القضية هنا.
These were questions that were all about, how well do you know your country?
وكانت هذه أسئلة تدور كلها حول مدى معرفتك ببلدك؟
So in this case, it's how well do you know 64 million people?
لذلك في هذه الحالة، ما مدى معرفتك بـ 64 مليون شخص؟
Not very well, it turns out. I can't do that.
ليس جيدًا علي ما يبدو، لا أستطيع أن أفعل ذلك.
So I had an idea,
لذلك كان لدي فكرة
which was to think about this same sort of approach
والتي كانت التفكير علي نفس النهج
but to think about it in a very local sense.
ولكن بطريقة محلية.
Is this a local?
هل هذا محلي؟
If we reframe the questions and say,
إذا قمنا بإعادة صياغة الأسئلة وسألنا
how well do you know your local area,
ما مدى معرفتك بمنطقثك المحلية
would your answers be any more accurate?
هل ستكون إجاباتك أكثر دقة؟
So I devised a quiz:
لذلك ابتكرت اختبارً:
How well do you know your area?
ما درجة معرفتك بمنطقتك؟
It's a simple Web app.
انه تطبيق بسيط على شبكة الإنترنت.
You put in a post code
أنت تدخل الرقم البريدي
and then it will ask you questions based on census data
وبعد ذلك سوف يسألك أسئلة استناًدا على بيانات الاحصاء
for your local area.
في منطقتك.
And I was very conscious in designing this.
وكنت واعيًا جدًا عند تصميمه.
I wanted to make it open to the widest possible range of people,
أردت أن أجعله مفتوحًا إلى أوسع نطاق ممكن من الناس،
not just the 49 percent who can get the numbers.
وليس فقط 49 في المئة الذين يمكنهم التعامل مع الأرقام.
I wanted everyone to engage with it.
أردت أن يتفاعل الجميع معه.
So for the design of the quiz,
لذا من أجل تصميم هذا الاختبار،
I was inspired by the isotypes
كان مستوحى من أنماط
of Otto Neurath from the 1920s and '30s.
أوتو نيوراث بالعشرينيات والثلاثينيات.
Now, these are methods for representing numbers
وهي أساليب لتمثيل الأرقام
using repeating icons.
باستخدام الرموز المتكررة.
And the numbers are there, but they sit in the background.
والأرقام موجودة ولكن في الخلفية.
So it's a great way of representing quantity
لذلك فهي طريقة رائعة لتمثيل الكمية
without resorting to using terms like "percentage,"
دون اللجوء إلى استخدام المصطلحات مثل "النسبة المئوية"،
"fractions" and "ratios."
"الكسور" و "النسب".
So here's the quiz.
هذا هو الاختبار.
The layout of the quiz is,
تصميم هذا الاختبار يعتمد علي،
you have your repeating icons on the left-hand side there,
لديك رمزك المتكرر على الجانب الأيسر،
and a map showing you the area we're asking you questions about
وخريطة تظهر لك المنطقة التي نطرح عليك أسئلة حولها
on the right-hand side.
على الجانب الأيمن،
There are seven questions.
هناك سبعة أسئلة.
Each question, there's a possible answer between zero and a hundred,
لكل سؤال هناك إجابة ممكنة بين 0 و 100
and at the end of the quiz,
وفي نهاية هذا الاختبار،
you get an overall score between zero and a hundred.
تحصل على النتيجة الإجمالية بين 0 و 100.
And so because this is TEDxExeter,
وذلك لأن هذا هو TEDxExeter
I thought we would have a quick look at the quiz
اعتقدت أنه يمكننا القاء نظرة سريعة على الاختبار
for the first few questions of Exeter.
بالنسبة للأسئلة القليلة الأولى حول إكزتر.
And so the first question is:
هكذا فإن السؤال الأول هو
For every 100 people, how many are aged under 16?
لكل 100 شخص، كم من هم دون سن 16 عامًا؟
Now, I don't know Exeter very well at all, so I had a guess at this,
الآن، أنا لا أعرف إكزتر بشكل جيد على الإطلاق لذلك إضطررت للتخمين،
but it gives you an idea of how this quiz works.
ولكنها تعطيك فكرة عن كيفية عمل هذا الاختبار.
You drag the slider to highlight your icons,
يمكنك سحب شريط التمرير لتسليط الضوء على الرموز الخاصة بك
and then just click "Submit" to answer,
ثم اضغط على إرسال للإجابة،
and we animate away the difference between your answer and reality.
ونحن نعرض لك الفرق بين إجابتك والواقع.
And it turns out, I was a pretty terrible guess: five.
واتضح أن تخميني كان فظيعًا: خمسة.
How about the next question?
ماذا عن السؤال التالي؟
This is asking about what the average age is,
يسأل عن متوسط ​​الأعمار،
so the age at which half the population are younger
أي أن العمر الذي يكون نصف السكان أصغر سنًا
and half the population are older.
ونصف السكان أكبر سنًا.
And I thought 35 -- that sounds middle-aged to me.
أعتقد 35 - يبدو في منتصف العمر بالنسبة لي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Actually, in Exeter, it's incredibly young,
في الواقع، في إكزتر أصغر بشكل لا يصدق،
and I had underestimated the impact of the university in this area.
وكنت قد قللت من تأثير الجامعة في هذا المنطقة.
The questions get harder as you go through.
الأسئلة تزداد صعوبة كلما نمضي.
So this one's now asking about homeownership:
لذلك هذا يسأل عن ملكية المنازل
For every 100 households, how many are owned with a mortgage or loan?
لكل 100 أسرة، كم عدد المنازل المملوكة برهن عقاري أو قرض؟
And I hedged my bets here,
وقد أخذت حذري هنا،
because I didn't want to be more than 50 out on the answer.
لأنني لا أريد أن يكون جوابي خاطئًا بأكثر من 50.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And actually, these get harder, these questions,
وفي الواقع، تزداد هذه الأسئلة صعوبة،
because when you're in an area, when you're in a community,
لأنه عندما تكون في منطقة عندما تكون في مجتمع
things like age -- there are clues to whether a population is old or young.
أشياء مثل العمر - هناك تلميحات ما إذا كان السكان من كبار السن أو الشباب،
Just by looking around the area, you can see it.
فقط من خلال النظر في المنطقة، يمكنك أن ترى ذلك.
Something like homeownership is much more difficult to see,
شيء مثل ملكية البيت هو أكثر صعوبة بكثير،
so we revert to our own heuristics,
لذلك نعود إلى الاستدلالات الخاصة بنا
our own biases about how many people we think own their own homes.
تحيزاتنا الخاصة حول كم من الناس نحن نعتقد أنهم يملكون منازلهم.
Now the truth is, when we published this quiz,
لآنه في الحقيقة عندما نشرنا هذا الاختبار،
the census data that it's based on was already a few years old.
بيانات التعداد التي يقوم عليها كانت منذ بضع سنوات.
We've had online applications that allow you to put in a post code
كان لدينا تطبيقات عبر الإنترنت التي تسمح لك بوضع الرمز البريدي
and get statistics back for years.
والحصول على الإحصاءات منذ عدة سنوات.
So in some senses,
لذا فى بعض النواحى،
this was all a little bit old and not necessarily new.
كان هذا شيء قديم قليلًا وليس بالضرورة جديد.
But I was interested to see what reaction we might get
ولكن كنت مهتمًا أن أرى ردود الفعل التي نحصل عليها
by gamifying the data in the way that we have,
من جعل هذه البيانات على شكل ألعاب بالطريقة التي رأيناها،
by using animation
باستخدام الرسوم المتحركة
and playing on the fact that people have their own preconceptions.
واللعب على واقع أن الناس لديهم تصوراتهم الخاصة.
It turns out, the reaction was, um ...
اتضح أن رد الفعل كان
was more than I could have hoped for.
كان أكثر مما كنت أتمنى.
It was a long-held ambition of mine to bring down a statistics website
لقد كان طموحًا طال أمده لإسقاط موقع الإحصاءات
due to public demand.
بسبب ازدياد الطلب العام.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This URL contains the words "statistics," "gov" and "UK,"
يحتوي الرابط على هذه الكلمات (الإحصاءات) و(حكومة) و(المملكة المتحدة)،
which are three of people's least favorite words in a URL.
والتي هي ثلاثة من أقل الكلمات المفضلة في روابط البحث.
And the amazing thing about this was that the website came down
والشيء المدهش حول هذا هو أن الموقع قد تعطل
at quarter to 10 at night,
قي العاشرة إلا ربع مساءً،
because people were actually engaging with this data
لأن الناس كانوا منخرطين مع هذه البيانات
of their own free will,
بإرادتهم الحرة،
using their own personal time.
مستخدمين وقتهم الشخصي.
I was very interested to see
كنت مهتمًا جدًا أن أرى
that we got something like a quarter of a million people
أن حصلنا علي شيء مثل ربع مليون شخص
playing the quiz within the space of 48 hours of launching it.
يقومون بالاختبار فى غضون 48 ساعة من إطلاقه.
And it sparked an enormous discussion online, on social media,
وأثارت مناقشة هائلة على شبكة الإنترنت وعلى وسائل التواصل الاجتماعية،
which was largely dominated
الذي كان يهيمن عليه إلى حد كبير
by people having fun with their misconceptions,
من قبل الناس يلهون مع مفاهيمهم الخاطئة
which is something that I couldn't have hoped for any better,
وهو شيء لم أكن آمل أفضل منه،
in some respects.
في بعض النواحي.
I also liked the fact that people started sending it to politicians.
أحب أيضًا حقيقة أن الناس بدئوا في إرسالها إلى السياسيين.
How well do you know the area you claim to represent?
ما جودة معرفتك بالمنطقة التي تمثلها؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then just to finish,
ثم في النهاية،
going back to the two kinds of people,
بالعودة إلى النوعين من الناس،
I thought it would be really interesting to see
اعتقدت أنه سيكون مثيرًا للاهتمام حقًا
how people who are good with numbers would do on this quiz.
أن نرى كيف أبلى الأشخاص الجيدين مع الأرقام في هذا الاختبار
The national statistician of England and Wales, John Pullinger,
الخبير الإحصائي الوطني في انجلترا وويلز، جون بولينج،
you would expect he would be pretty good.
تتوقع أنه سيكون جيدًا جدًا،
He got 44 for his own area.
حصل على 44 لمنطقته.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Jeremy Paxman -- admittedly, after a glass of wine -- 36.
جيريمي باكسمان - باعتراف الجميع، بعد كوب من النبيذ - 36،
Even worse.
أسوء حتى.
It just shows you that the numbers can inspire us all.
يظهر لك فقط أن الأرقام يمكنها أن تلهمنا جميعًا،
They can surprise us all.
ويمكنها أن تفاجئنا جميعًا.
So very often, we talk about statistics
حتى في كثير من الأحيان نحن نتحدث عن الإحصاء
as being the science of uncertainty.
باعتباره علم عدم اليقين.
My parting thought for today is:
فكرتي الأخيرة لهذا اليوم هي
actually, statistics is the science of us.
في الواقع، الإحصاء هي علم عنا،
And that's why we should be fascinated by numbers.
وهذا هو السبب في أننا يجب أن نكون مفتونين بالأرقام.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)